<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="cookbook-chapter/out/cookbook.odd.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:ehfoodways="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ehfoodways/ns/1.0">
   
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Test Data for Cookbook Chapter</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <front>
        <titlePage>
           <docTitle>
              <titlePart><title>The Jamaican Cookery Book</title>
              <title type="subtitle">Three Hundred and Sixty-Four Simple Cookery
              Receipts and Household Hints Collected By <persName>Caroline Sullivan</persName></title>
              </titlePart>
                
             
              </docTitle>
        
        </titlePage>
        
     </front>
   <body>
     <div type="preface">
      <p>I do not think I am
        mistaken in saying that up to the present time a
         book on native cookery has never been produced in Jamaica: and it is to
         supply that want that I place before the public the few simple receipts
         it has been my pleasant occupation to gather together from time to
         time. I am quite aware that the various methods of cooking here
         mentioned may be open to criticism. There are doubtless ways known
         superior to those a knowledge of which I have succeeded in obtaining.
         But faulty as they may be, I venture to hope that those here given may
         be of some assistance to <emph>new comers</emph>, on whose especial
         behalf this work has been undertaken.</p>
         <p>I do not venture to offer any hints to those whose long residence in
         the island renders them familiar with all the details of our ordinary
         Jamaica cooking; but from them I should be glad to receive notes on any
         articles which I may have omitted.</p>
         <p>I have carefully refrained from giving European cookery, and have
            confined myself entirely to the every day dishes which come under
            immediate notice in this island. Simple as these receipts may be,
            should any of them prove to be of help and use, I shall feel amply
            repaid for any trouble I may have taken in collecting them.
         <addName>C.S.</addName></p>
         <dateline>St. Andrew, Jamaica. December, 1893</dateline>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Preface to the Second Edition</head>
         <p>The kind appreciation with which my Jamaica Cookery Book has been
            generally received, encourages me to place a second edition of it
            before the public. Since its publication, I have been fortunate
            enough to collect between sixty and seventy additional receipts,
            which may I trust, prove of some small service to those in need of
            them, as the others have been.
            <persName>Caroline Sullivan</persName></p>
         <dateline>St. Andrew, Jamaica. November, 1897</dateline>
      </div>
            <!-- table of contents -->
         <div>
            <div type="section">
            <head>I. — SOUPS.</head>
            <div type="recipe" ana="native">
               <head>1. Turtle Soup</head>
               <div type="orientationNote">
               <p>This is
              prepared in many ways, some preferring it thin, others thick: a
              good family soup may be made as follows:—</p></div>
             
               <div type="list">
              <list type="simple">
                 <item>Two lbs. of Turtle stew meat.</item>
              <item>Cloves, cinnamon, and mace</item>
                 <item>One quart and one pint of water,</item>
                 <item>One large onion or some skellion</item>
                 <item>A sprig of parsley.</item>
                 <item>Some herbs</item>
                 <item>A few tomatoes</item>
                 <item>Six cloves.</item>
                 <item>A piece of salt pork and a piece of salt beef</item>
                 <item>Thickening of flour.</item>
                 <item>Sauce, lime juice. salt and cayenne pepper.</item>
                 <item>One wineglassful of sherry.</item>
           </list>
               </div>
               <div type="instructions">
                  <p>
                     Get two lbs. of <ehfoodways:nativeIngredient type="meat">turtle stew meat</ehfoodways:nativeIngredient> or a little less, and stew it down
             the day before you make your soup, with cloves, cinnamon and mace;
             next day put the stew and its gravy into a quart and pint of water
             with half a pound of turtle soup meat; add an onion or some
             skellion (some people put a turnip and a carrot) some parsley,
             herbs and tomatoes. When it has boiled half an hour, add the salt
             pork and salt beef cut in pieces. Let it boil another hour, then
             remove any fat there may be, which cut in dice, and put it in the
             tureen with some of the soft gristle as well. Let the soup boil
             another half hour, adding water if too low; then strain it through
             a cullender. Put the strained soup back in the pot, and put in a
             good tablespoonful of flour previously mixed smooth with water and
             poured in; then add a little Worcester or Harvey's sauce, the juice
             of a lime, some salt, a little cayenne and stir till it is nice and
             think like cream. Pour this over the fat and gristle dice in the
             tureen and serve, adding just before serving a wineglassful of
             sherry.</p>
               </div>
            <!-- I want to track process (stew, braise). spices. meat. veg.  -->
         </div>
      <div>
         <head>2. Ochro Soup.</head>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>Two dozen ochros.</item>
            <item>One and a half pound of salt beef</item>
            <item>Two quarts of water.</item>
            <item>Seasoning, tomato and skellion and thyme</item>
            <item>Indian kale or callilu</item>
            <item>Penny halfpenny worth of salt pork</item>
         </list>
         <p>
         Put the ochros into the water and boil until the seeds get red: then
         add the pork and beef and go on boiling, adding the seasoning and other
         ingredients. Chop fine some kale or callilu and add to the soup, and
         serve. It can be strained if preferred. A few black crabs boiled and
         added to the soup make it excellent.</p>
      </div>
               
      <div>
         <head>3. Sugar Bean soup</head>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>Penny halfpenny worth of green fresh sugar beans.</item>
            <item>One quart and one pint of water.</item>
            <item>Some bones of soup meat and a little salt pork.</item>
            <item>Black pepper, skellion and herbs</item>
         </list>
            <p>Boil the beans in the water putting it on in cold water. When
               half done add a little soup meat and some salt pork. If
               preferred, the beans are left in the soup and it is then served
               unstrained. Children are especially fond of it, particularly if a
            little potato or yam be boiled in it also. The addition of a few
            tomatoes is according to taste.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head><q>Bannabis</q> soup</head>
         <p>This is a large bean, and the soup made from it is particularly
            delicate.</p>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>One pint Bannabis beans.</item>
            <item>One quart water</item>
            <item>Half a cocoanut made into milk.</item>
            <item>Herbs.</item>
         </list>
            <p>A small piece of salt beef and the same of salt pork (or a beef
               bone or a bit of ham or a tongue bone. Soak the beans for about
               an hour or more in cold water. Then take them out and strip off
               the skin and put them into a quart of hot water. Boil half an
               hour, then add the beef, pork and herbs. Now grate the cocoanut
               and squeeze out as much milk from it as you can, wringing it
               through a cloth. This is to be added to the soup just before
               serving, well stirred in; but the soup itself takes from one hour
               to one and a half to boil
            </p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>5. <ehfoodways:nativeIng class="vegetable">Goongoo Peas Soup.</ehfoodways:nativeIng></head>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>One quart of water. Seasoning.</item>
            <item>One half pint of dry goongoos</item>
            <item>A penny half penny worth of either salt beef or salt pork.</item>
         </list>
            <p>Put the peas in cold water (about a quart) and let them boil for
               two hours and a half with a sprig of thyme and a piece of
               skellion. <unclear> then</unclear>rub through a cullender smooth and thick, and
                  serve with sippets of dry toast handed. Add the salt pork
                  about half an hour after the peas have been on the fire.</p>
      </div>
               
               
      <!-- Using Red Peas Soup to model different ways of marking -->         
               
      <div type="recipe" >
         <head>6. Red Peas Soup</head><note>N.R.—<ehfoodways:cultDist>The natives do not strain their
         peas soup: they eat the whole thing boiled with yam, coco and dumplings
         and often with a remarkable concoction called
            <ehfoodways:nativeIngredient class="vegetable"><soCalled>"foo foo"</soCalled></ehfoodways:nativeIngredient> which consists
         of yam or coco boiled and beaten and then added to the soup.</ehfoodways:cultDist> Needless
         to say, this makes them a decidedly substantial repast. The dumplings
         are often made with equal parts of flour and cornmeal.</note>
         <list type="simple">
            <item>One pint of peas.</item>
            <item>Two quarts of water.</item>
            <item>Penny-half-penny worth of salt pork.</item>
            </list>
         <p>Put the peas into cold water and boil three hours till the peas are
            soft, adding penny-half-penny worth of salt pork about two hours and
            a half after boiling has begun. At the end of three hours time press
            the peas through a cullender. Serve with dry toast cut in dice.</p>
      </div>
      
           <div>
                  <head>6. Red Peas Soup</head>
                  <div type="orientationNote">
                     <p>N.R.—The natives do not strain their
                     peas soup: they eat the whole thing boiled with yam, coco and dumplings
                     and often with a remarkable concoction called "foo foo" which consists
                     of yam or coco boiled and beaten and then added to the soup. Needless
                     to say, this makes them a decidedly substantial repast. The dumplings
                     are often made with equal parts of flour and cornmeal.</p></div>
                  <div type="list">
                  <list type="simple">
                     <item>One pint of peas.</item>
                     <item>Two quarts of water.</item>
                     <item>Penny-half-penny worth of salt pork.</item>
                  </list></div>
                  <div type="instructions">
                  <p>Put the peas into cold water and boil three hours till the peas are
                     soft, adding penny-half-penny worth of salt pork about two hours and
                     a half after boiling has begun. At the end of three hours time press
                     the peas through a cullender. Serve with dry toast cut in dice.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
      
      
      
         <div>
            <head>7. White Peas Soup.</head>
            <p>This is prepared in the same way as red peas soup.</p>
         </div>
      <div>
         <head>8. Cockle Cress Soup.</head>
         <list>
            <item>1 Pint of cockle cress peas.</item>
            <item>1 Quart of water.</item>
            <item>Skellion, tomatoes</item>
            <item>Salt pork.</item>
         </list>
         <p>Put the peas on to boil for two hours and a half putting them on in
            cold water, with the tomatos (a few) and one large skellion. About
            one hour afterwards add the salt pork (or beef or ham or tongue
            bone) and at the end of another hour and a half rub through a
            callender smooth and thick. Serve, and hand sippets of dry toast to
            eat with it.</p>
      </div>
   <div>
      <head>9. Coco Soup</head>
      <p>This is a favourite dish amongst the peasantry, especially in the
         country parts where fresh meat is scarce.</p>
      <list>
         <item>1 quart of water</item>
         <item>Three large cocos.</item>
         <item>A penny half penny worth of salt pork and the same of salt
            beef.</item>
         <item>Some dumplings, a little bunch of seasoning and some skellion and
            tomatos.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Cut the cocos in halves and put into the water to boil. In about a
         quarter of an hour, add the pork, beef and seasonings. Boil another
         quarter of an hour. Then mash up the cocos fine and thick, and serve
         with some tiny dumplings, any size or shape desired.</p>
   </div>
      <div>
         <head>10. Callilu Soup.</head>
         <p>This is another of the country soups very often used by the people.</p>
         <list>
            <item>One quart of water.</item>
            <item>One small bunch of callilu.</item>
            <item>A slice of salt pork and the same of salt beef.</item>
           </list>
         <p>Trim the callilu by taking off the rough scaly bits from the leaves,
            and then put it into some boiling water for about a quarter of an
            hour. Throw away that water and put on a quart of water to boil,
            meanwhile take the callilu and chop it very fine indeed, then add it
            to the water: boil a quarter of an hour and then add the beef and
            pork. In another quarter of an hour it will be fit for table.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>11. Shrimp Soup.</head>
         <list>
            <item>One pound of fish.
            </item>
            <item>One quart and one pint of water.</item>
            <item>Half a pound of shrimps.</item>
            <item>Pepper and salt, thyme, lime-peel and skellion.</item>
            <item>A penny half-penny worth of salt pork or beef.</item>
            <item>A teaspoonful of butter.</item>
            <item>Two cloves.</item>
            <item>A little sauce and a squeeze of lime.</item>
        </list>
         <p>Boil the fish in the quart and pint of water till reduced to a
            quart. Pick the shrimps and pound the heads, tails and skins fine,
            then put this and the shrimps into the fish stock, removing the
            fish. Put in the butter and seasoning and cloves. Boil ten minutes.
            Take out the shrimps, cut in small pieces and put in the soup
            tureen. Boil the rest of the ingredients in the stock another half
            hour. Thicken with a little flour and pour over the shrimps, adding
            a squeeze of lime.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>12. Lobster Soup</head>
           <p>Make a little stock first of any kind of fish, till it makes one
              pint.</p>
         <list>
            <item>One lobster.</item>
            <item>Pepper and salt, parsley, thyme, lime-peel, bread crumbs and
               onion</item>
            <item>Butter, milk and nutmeg</item>
      </list>
         <p>Boil the lobster, seasoning the water it was boiled in; put all the
            meat of it, <emph>except the tail ends and any corals</emph>, into a
            mortar with the shell and pound it all together as fine as
            possibe<sic>possible</sic>. Add this to the fish soup stock, and the
            water the lobster was boiled in; season with pepper and salt,
            parsley, thyme, lime-peel and some bread crumbs and an onion. Simmer
            quietly for nearly two hours, then strain it off. Have ready the
            tail end of the lobsters chopped into dice and the lobster corals
            which put into the tureen. Add a little milk and a desertspoonful of
            butter and some nutmeg to the soup and give it one boil; pour into
            the tureen, and serve: some people like force-meat balls added to
            this soup.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>13. Jonga Soup.</head>
         <p>This is prepared similarly to cray fish or bisque soup.</p>
         <p>Half a dozen large jongas, butter, seasoning, grated lime-peel,
            bread crumbs, onion or skellion and milk.</p>
         <p>Half fry the jongas in butter, then pound both flesh and shells
            together (but reserve one or two whole to cut into dice to serve
            with the soup); pound them in a mortar, season highly, adding some
            grated lime peel, bread crumbs, onion or skellion with the usual
            herbs. Boil gently for one hour, strain and put back in the pot for
            a little with the jongas cut in dice, add a little butter (about a
            teaspoonful) and half a cupful of milk. Stir well and serve hot.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>14. Ackee Soup</head>
         <p>Take 12 ackees: pick them well taking out the pink part. Put them
            into a piece of muslin, and boil them. Put on one quart of water,
            one pound of beef, a small piece of salt pork or salt beef to make
            it tasty: also some seasoning, thyme and skellion. Mash the ackees
            quite smooth and mix them with the soup and boil them all
            together.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>15. Cocoanut Soup</head>
         <list>
            <item>One lb. of beef. One quart of water.</item>
            <item>One small piece of salt pork or beef.</item>
            <item>Two small white cocos.</item>
            <item>Skellion, thyme.</item>
            <item>One cocoanut.</item>
            <item>Half a pint of hot water.</item>
         </list>
         <p>Put on one lb. of beef with a piece of salt beef or salt pork, two
            small white cocos and some skellion and thyme, in one quart of water
            to boil. Boil it down to one pint. Grate a small cocoanut, throw
            half a pink of hot water on it, then squeeze out the milk. Pour this
            milk into the soup and boil up, once. Before putting the cocoanut
            milk into the soup, the soup must be quite boiled and strained, then
            add the milk to the boiling soup. Stir well, and serve at once.</p>
      </div>
           <div>
               <head>16. Pepper Pot</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Three tablespoonfuls of pure casseripe to every quart of
                  water, cold. Salt to taste.</item>
                  <item>One handful of bird peppers.</item>
                  <item>Meat, eggs.</item> 
                 
               </list>
               <p>Get an earthen vessel. To every quart of cold water, add three
                  tablespoonfuls of the pure caseripe with salt to taste and a
                  handful of bird peppers. If these cannot be had, use some
                  cayene. Cut the meat into small pieces after being well
                  cooked, and put into the pot; boil well for half an hour. Any
                  sort of meat may be used, all mixed in it, and hard boiled
                  eggs are an improvement. It should be warmed every day, and
                  something added each day.</p>
            </div>
      <div>
         <head>17. Pumpkin Soup</head>
         <list>
            <item>One large slice of pumkin or half a small pumkin.</item>
            <item>One quart and a pint of water.</item>
            <item>Either some soup meat or a little salt pork or salt beef.</item>
            <item>Black pepper, thyme.</item>
            
         </list>
            <p>Cut up the pumkin and add to the water (either cold or hot),
               putting with it the soup meat if fresh meat and a little thyme
               and black pepper; in about half an hour's time add if liked a
               small bit of salt pork or salt beef, or else salt to taste. In
               about another half hour strain the soup through a cullender and
               serve curried: this soup is particularly palatable.</p>
      </div>
         </div>
      <div>
         <head>II. FISH</head>
         <p>Snappers, mullet, king-fish, mackerel, old wife, calepeaver,
            cutlass, mountain mullet, lobsters, crayfish, oysters, jongas, crabs
            shrimps and turtle all have their season in Jamaica.</p>
         <p>There are two sorts of crabs the white and the black. The former are
            not generally eaten being foul feeders, but the black crabs are
            highly esteemed and are counted among the delicacies of Jamaica.</p>
         <div>
            <head>18. King-Fish</head>
            <p>This is a much esteemed fish, and is good cooked in any way.
               Boiled and served with butter and parsley or oyster or anchovy
               sauce, it must be appreciated by everyone. King-fish steaks, that
               is king-fish cut up in thick slices and broiled with onions, are
               excellent, especially if a rich brown gravy be added. Opened and
               stuffed with bread-crumbs and oysters and served with tomato
               sauce they make a rich and agreeable dish.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>19. Mountain Mullet</head>
            <p>These are esteemed ome of Jamaica's delicacies. They are of
               excellent flavour, but the drawback to them in many people's
               opinion is the number of small bones they possess. The nicest way
               of cooking them is rolling them in buttered paper and frying
               them, sending them to table in the paper: but they can of course
               be fried plain or boiled if preferred.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>20. Cutlass</head>
            <p>This is a long ribbony fish and it has small bones at the side,
               which must be carefully taken away: very good cutlets can be made
               of this fish, but they make excellent fish cakes or fish pies.
               They do well for Kedgeree, a mixture of boiled rice, picked fish,
               mustard, butter and curry powder.</p>
      </div>
         <div>
            <head>21. Calepeaver</head>
            <p>This fish is sometimes called the Salmom of Jamaica. It is a very
            rich delicately flavoured fish: it is more often to be had in the
            vicinity of Spanish Town. The size varies, but they are sometimes
            very fine and large. The best way of cooking this fish is to boil
            it; putting it on (after carefully cleansing it and rubbing it with
            lime-juice) in hot water with a little salt in it, boiling slowly;
            allowing ten minutes boiling to each pound of fish. Shrimp and
            butter sauce or oyster sauce are good additions, but perhaps butter
            and parsley is best, and a cut lime handed to squeeze over.</p>
        </div>
         <div>
            <head>22. Jongas</head>
            <p>Jongas, are a kind of small cray-fish which are often found in
               the mountain rivers. They are cooked like lobsters, and make an
               excellent stew or fricassee or curry.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>23. Oysters</head>
            <p>Of these there are two sorts, the round or raw-eaten oyster, and
               the flat or cooking oyster. The former are small but very
               delicate in flavour; they can of course also be cooked. The flat
               oyster is the best for scallops or patties, or in any cooked
               form. The way to open these is by placing them near the fire when
               the shells open of themselves.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>24. Roasted Lobster</head>
            <p>More than half boil it. Then take it out of the water and shell
               it as quickly as possible. While hot, rub it well with butter,
               put it in a Dutch oven, baste it well until nicely frothed, and
               serve with melted butter.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>25. Lobster Croquettes</head>
            <list>
               <item>One small lobster.</item>
               <item>Seasoning, tomato, and pepper, spices, one onion,
                  lime-juice, lime-peel, salt, butter, milk, grated bread, two
                  eggs.</item>
            </list>
               <p>Shell a small lobster and chop it fine with seasoning and
                  nutmeg, onion, tomato, pepper and thyme, with a little grated
                  lime-peel and some of the juice of the lime and some salt. Add
                  a dessert spoonful of butter and about as much cream or milk
                  and two table-spoonfuls of breaded bread. Mix all together
                  with two beaten eggs: make balls, roll in egg and bread crumb,
                  and fry. Put either a rich white sauce or brown gravy in the
                  dish, the croquettes on the top, and serve very hot.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>26. Baked Lobster</head>
            <list>
               <item>One tablespoonful of butter.</item>
               <item>Plenty of pepper and salt</item>
               <item>Worcester sauce. Jamaica pepper, vinegar, bread crumbs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Boil the lobster, then shell and pick it and chop it fine. Add a
               tablespoonful of butter, plenty of pepper and salt, a little
               Worcester sauce and some Jamaica pepper just to flavour or some
               pepper-wine, a little vinegar too. Mix all well together; put it
               in a small buttered pie-dish, bread-crumb it, put a little dab or
               so of butter here and there, and bake.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>27. Lobster Cutlets</head>
            <list>
               <item>Half a lb. of lobster.</item>
               <item>Two ozs. of butter</item>
               <item>Two teaspoonfuls of chopped onions.</item>
               <item>One teaspoonfuls of flour.</item>
               <item>Water, milk, salt, pepper, cayenne, parsley, yolks of two
                  eggs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Cut up the lobster, letting the flesh (in dice) weigh <unclear>1
               lb</unclear>. Put in a saucepan two oz of butter, two
               teaspoonfuls of chopped onions; add the lobster and fry for a
               minute or two. Add one teaspoonful of flour mixed smooth with
               water, stir in: add half a pint of milk, salt, pepper, and
               cayenne, two teaspoons of chopped parsley. Let it boil a little,
               stirring all the time; add the lobster, give it a boil, add the
               two yolks of eggs: mix quickly and put in a dish to cool. When
               cool and firm divide into six parts and shape like cutlets; egg
               and bread crumb twice. Put a piece of the very small claw to the
               end of each cutlet so as to form a bone. Fry for a few minutes as
               you would a sole, in plenty of lard or fat; lay on a cloth, and
               serve on a napkin with a plenty of parsley. No sauce is needed.
               The lobster may be prepared shaped and bread crumbed some hours
               before wanted.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>28. Old Wife</head>
            <p>These are queer flat fish. They should be cooked like the English
               sole. Wash them carefully and dry them well, then dust over a
               little flour; egg and bread-crumb them, and fry a light brown,
               turning them when one side is done. Serve with metled butter and
               garnish with parsley.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>29. June Fish</head>
            <p>A cottony fish. It should be stewed in a rich brown sauce with
               onions, tomatoes, and herbs, and a wineglass of port wine added
               towards the end of the cooking and thickening with a little
               flour. A little fresh pepper makes an agreeable addition, but
               very little.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>30. Baked Fish No. 1</head>
         
         <p>Clean, rinse, and wipe dry any kind of fish; rub with salt and
            pepper; fill with stuffing, the same as for poultry only drier. Sew
            up and put in a pan with some hot dripping and a lump of butter.
            Dredge with flour, and lay over the fish a few thin slices of salt
            pork or bits of butter. Bake one hour and a half, basting
            occasionally.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>31. Baked Fish No. 2</head>
            <p>Any cold fish, maccaroni, milk, butter, grated cheese,
               bread-crumbs and cayenne.</p>
            <p>Boil some maccaroni very tender in milk, about twice as much
               maccaroni as there is cold fish, which should be broken in small
               pieces and the bones removed.</p>
            <p>Mix with it the maccaroni cut in dice, the grated cheese and
               cayenne. Put it in a flat dish with bread crumbs and some pieces
               of butter on the top and bake a light brown. Any fish will do for
               this dish.</p>
         </div>
               <div>
                  <head>32. Turtle Cutlets</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>One and a half lbs. of turtle steak</item>
                     <item>Onions.</item>
                     <item>Pepper, lime juice, salt, bread or biscuit crumbs,
                        nutmeg, tomato, skellion, two eggs</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Cut the turtle into cutlets, rub well with onion, and
                     sprinkle well with pepper, sauce and lime-juice. Get ready
                     some bread or biscuit crumbs; add nutmeg and some onion or
                     skellion and tomatoes finely minced: dip the cutlets into
                     the eggs previously stirred in a plate, then into the
                     seasoned crumbs; cover well, and fry, serving with cut lime
                     and parsley.</p>
               </div>
         <div>
            <head>33. Turtle Balls</head>
                 <list>
                    <item>Turtle, one and a half lbs.</item>
                    <item>Seasoning.</item>
                    <item>A small piece of salt beef</item>
                    <item>Tomato, skellion, lime-juice, salt, herbs, two eggs.</item>
                    <item>One tablespoonful of sherry.</item>
                 </list>
            <p>Mince the beef and turtle together very fine, add some chopped
               tomatoes, skellions, herbs, salt and a very little Jamaica fresh
               pepper: add a squeeze of lime juice, a little sauce a
               tablespoonful of sherry, a little spice and two well-beaten eggs.
               Make into balls and fry, sending them to table with a rich well
               seasoned brown gravy, to which add another teaspooful of sherry
               and lime.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>34. Turtle Steak</head>
            <list>
               <item>Two lbs. of turtle steak-meat.</item>
               <item>Lime juice, lard, pepper, onions, tomatoes, flour,
                  butter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Rub the steak well with lime juice. Have ready some boiling lard
               in a frying pan. Put in the meat whole. (Some people it cut in
               pieces, but it is really best done whole, or it is likely to get
               tough or dry.) Put with it some black pepper and sliced onions
               and tomatoes. Cover it over a little; when half done it will make
               its own gravy, but if not quite enough, add a tablespoonful of
               water, and if a thick gravy is liked a little flour and butter
               rubbed smoothly together with the water. The steak takes from
               twenty minutes to half na hour to cook.</p>
            <p>Serve with the fat put on the top of the meat, squeeze some
               lime-juice over the whole and garnish with cut lime and slices of
               onion and tomatoes</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>35. Turtle Stew</head>
            <list>
               <item>Two lbs. of turtle stew meat.</item>
               <item>One quart of water.</item>
               <item>Salt, lime juice.</item>
               <item>Cinnamon, nutmeg, pepper, ten cloves, one onion, a few
                  tomatoes, parsley, thyme, sherry.</item>
               <item>Two pounds of turtle stew meat.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Wash the meat well with salt and lime-juice and put it into a
               quart of cold water; then add a stick of cinnamon, a large onion,
               a few tomatoes, some parsley, thyme, herbs and pepper.</p>
            <p>Stew gently for three hours, adding water now and then if it gets
               too low. About a quarter of an hour before serving, mix a good
               tablespoonful of flour smoothly with a little water, sufficiently
               liquid to pour into the pot to thicken the stew. Stir; at the
               last minute put in a desert spoonful of sauce and half a glass of
               sherry; mix well, and serve with a cut lime to squeeze over the
               meat. </p>
         </div>
                  <div>
                     <head>36. Black-Crabs, Boiled</head>
                     <p>These are liked either plain, boiled, or "<q>baked in the
                        back</q>" as the expression is. Plain boiled, they come
                        to table whole and they have really more flavour that
                        way, but there are many small bones and there is much
                        difficulty in eating them <emph>at table</emph>. The
                        claws contain the principal meat; the back is to be
                        opened and the gall removed; the black water inside
                        possesses much flavour. When in full season the eggs are
                        numerous and excellent: boiled in soup they are
                        delicious.</p>
                  </div>
         <div>
            <head>37. Black-Crabs, Baked</head>
            <list>
               <item>A dozen crabs boiled.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Carefully pick the meat from all the claws and smaller bones (it
               takes a long time and careful picking): then open the backs and
               extract the eggs, throwing away the galls and putting aside the
               black water to be added at the last. When all the picking is
               done, put to the meat two tablespoonfuls of butter, a teaspoonful
               of black pepper, a dessertspoonful of sauce of pepper-vinegar, a
               little cayenne and some nutmeg. Mix well, adding salt to taste,
               and fill as many of the backs as you can, leaving room for a
               dressings of bread-crumbs on which dabs of butter are placed to
               moisten. Before putting the meat into the backs, put one or two
               eggs in each shell and do not forget to mix in the black water,
               as that has the full black-crab flavour. The twelve crabs ought
               to make ten good crab-back fillings.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>38. Land Turtle or Terrapin</head>
            <p>Cut off the head, and open the back. Remove the flesh from the
               inside and take away the bones, and also get what meat you can
               from the legs: Scald it with boiling water to remove the outer
               skin. Chop the meat into dice, adding a small piece of salt pork
               and salt beef, some tomatoes, skellion, herbs and black pepper
               with some cinnamon and nutmeg: add some sauce, butter,
               lime-juice, and a glass of sherry: mix all well and put into the
               turtle-back. Bread crumb the top, put dabs of butter here and
               there and bake in the shell. As there is not much meat in these
               turtle, it will take two turtle to fill one back. 
            </p>                  
         </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>III. SALT FISH.</head>
         <p>It is suprising to most new-comers, to find that in Jamaica there is
            hardly a more popular dish among the natives and often among the
            upper classes than the despised salt fish, eaten at home not from
            choice, but as a sort of penitential dish. Here, it is the almost
            daily, and certainly the favourite food of the people generally; and
            cooked, <emph>as they cook it</emph>, it cannot fail to please the
            most fastidious. </p>
         <p>The following are a few of the favourite methods of preparing it.</p>
         <div>
            <head>39. Salt Fish and Akees</head>
            <list>
               <item>One lb of saltfish  </item>
               <item>The fruit of twelve ackee pods.</item>
               <item>Lard, butter and black pepper</item>
            </list>
            <p>Soak the salt-fish over night. Put it on in cold water to boil,
               otherwise it hardens: throw off the first water and put it on
               again to boil. Carefully pick the ackees free from all red
               inside, which is dangerous, and boil them for about twenty
               minutes; add them to the saltfish which is then cut in small
               pieces; add some lard, butter and pepper. Some prefer the
               saltfish and ackees mashed together and the melted lard and
               butter poured over the top.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>40. Salt Fish and Rice</head>
            <p>This is a favourite native dish. The saltfish and rice, about a
               half a pound of salt fish to a pint of rice, are boiled together
               with the usual bit of salt pork and a little butter.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>41. Salt Fish Fritters No. 1</head>
            <p>Some people add an egg or perhaps two to salt-fish and rice, and
               make fritters of it for breakfast.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>42. Salt Fish Fritters No. 2</head>
            <p>Boiled salt-fish and ackees mixed together with pepper and
               seasoning make excellent fritters. No egg is required.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>43. Salt Fish Fritters No. 3</head>
            <list>
               <item>Half a lb. of salt-fish</item>
               <item>Jamaica pepper</item>
               <item>Tomatoes, skellions, butter, lard, parsley and two eggs.</item>
            </list>
                  <p>Boil half a pound of the fish and mash it fine with some
                     seasoning, a tablespoonful of butter, a teaspoonful of
                     lard, a little chopped Jamaica fresh pepper (or some
                     cayenne) and some minced tomatoes, skellions and herbs. Mix
                     well with two well-beaten eggs and fry in fritters. These
                     are very good for breakfast.</p>
               </div>
         <div>
            <head>44. Salt Herrings</head>
            <p>Soak the herrings well. Then boil them changing the water once,
               or they may be too salt. Drain and serve with melted butter and
               parsley and garnished with slides of fresh pepper, fried onions
               and tomatoes.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>45. Salt Mackerel</head>
            <p>Soak the fish some hours, then boil it, changing the water once
               to extract the salt. Put it on in cold water and let it come to a
               boil. Drain, and serve with butter, sauce, garnish with sliced
               lemons, tomatoes, and fresh peppers.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>46. Fried Salt Fish</head>
            <list>
               <item>Half a lb. of saltfish</item>
               <item>Onions, tomatoes</item>
               <item>Lard, butter, pepper.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Boil the fish first. Then cut it into pieces not too small, and
               fry with slices of onions and tomatoes, which serve on the top of
               the fish with slices of pepper and some parsley.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>47. Salt Mackerel Cutlets</head>
            <p>Soak the mackerel for some hours; boil it, putting it on in cold
               water. Then cut the fish into slices, egg and bread crumb, and
               fry with lard.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>48. Salt Fish twice-laid</head>
            <list>
               <item>Half a lb. of saltfish</item>
               <item>Four large potatoes or a good slice of any yam, except the
                  yampee which is too sweet</item>
               <item>One tablespoonful of butter</item>
               <item>One dessert spoonful of lard, skellion, parsley, pepper,
                  tomatoes, herbs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Boil the fish, chop and mix well with the potato or yam mashed,
               add the butter and lard, herbs, and other ingredients. Mix in two
               beaten eggs: butter a pie-dish, put in the mixture and bake a
               light brown.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>49. Curried Salt Fish</head>
            <p>Saltfish stewed in the way mentioned in these receipts, and then
               curried, with the addition of a spoonful of mustard, is a very
               acceptable dish. Put a tablespoonful of curry powder and a
               squeeze of lime-juice to the mixture, and serve with rice balls.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>50. Salt Fish and Susumbers</head>
            <p>Boil the salt-fish after soaking it a few hours; while boiling
               add some of the young susumber berries to the fish and boil till
               tender. They give it a bitterish taste highly appreciated by the
               natives, but not palatable to everybody, and one must be careful
               to choose the right kind of susumber as there are two sorts. This
               dish his served with melted butter and lard poured over it.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>51. Shredded Salt Fish</head>
            <p>Soak some saltfish two hours, pull it to pieces in shreds, and
               fry with lard adding skellions, tomatoes and pepper.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>52. Salt Fish Patties</head>
            <list>
               <item>Half a lb. of saltfish stewed.</item>
                  <item>Skellions, tomatoes, pepper, onion, butter, sauce,
                     parsley and herbs</item>
               </list>
            <p>Half a lb. of saltfish stewed with some skellions, tomatoes,
               pepper and a dessert spoonful of butter. Add a little sauce and
               nutmeg. Put in patty-pans lined with pastry. Cover and bake.</p>
         </div>
         </div>
      <div>
         <head>IV.— MEAT</head>
         <p>Beef, mutton, pork and poultry are to be had in all the markets all
            over the island, and in the country parts distant from a market,
            there are always butchers who supply pork, or goal mutton at 6d. per
            lb. Now and then a cow is killed in the district, and then notice is
            given.</p>
         <p>In this little work, I do not allude to any methods of dressing
            beef, sheep-mutton, pork or poultry; for my desire is merely to
            introduce to new-comers to Jamaica, our own native methods of
            cooking our own products, and by no means to attempt to cope with
            the many excellent works that at present exist on English or other
            cookery. It will be noticed therefore that nothing will be mentioned
            here except a few hints that may be of service to those who are
            strangers to our native dishes, provided as they must already be
            with cookery books which will guide them in the cooking of beef,
            mutton, pork or poultry.</p>
         <p>There will be some surprise and perhaps discomfort on the part of
            the new-comer who finds that beef of all cuts, is sold at the same
            price, 6d per lb. no matter what one orders, unless one arranges
            with the butcher to give beef without bone at 7 1/2d per lb.; this
            of course would only be practicable with a round a steak, or a
            fillet. But the butchers charge 6d per lb. for bone as well as meat,
            and sometimes one is disappointed to find that when the
            "<soCalled>meat</soCalled>" is delivered, one half of it is
            "<q>weigh-meat</q>" or large pieces of bone. Sheep mutton is sold at
            <unclear>15</unclear> per lb. sometimes 10 1/2d. Pork from 6d to 7
            1/2d oftener 7 1/2d; in the country parts it is always 6d the liver
            at 4 1/2d per lb., head 4 1/2d per lb. Poultry ought not to fetch
            more than 9d per lb. in the towns; 6d in the country parts, or at
            the highest 7 1/2d per lb. In and about Kingston the people hawk
            them about asking exhorbitant prices; it is always best to weigh
            them. Ducks vary from 10 1/2d to 15 per lb; turksy 15 per lb;
            pigeons is 6d a pair for the large 15 3d for the smaller. Wild birds
            vary in price, from the small ground dove at 3d each, to the larger
            birds going from 1<unclear>5</unclear> 15 6d, 2<unclear>5</unclear> to
               2<unclear>5</unclear> 6d and 3<unclear>5</unclear> a pair. Guinea
               Birds 2<unclear>s</unclear> 6d each or 3s. Wild Guinea Birds 2s
               6d each, or 5s to 6s per pair.</p>
      </div>
      
      <div>
            <head></head>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head></head>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head></head>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head></head>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head></head>
            
         </div>
   
   
   
   
   
   </body>
               
  </text>
</TEI>
